okay so today what I'd like to do is
talk about something that happens in the
context of some of the other things we
looked at if you recall the kinetic
framework which I think was maybe
episode two the distinction between the
complex and the complicated and in the
complicated what we noticed was that
making effective choices was relatively
straightforward which is to say that in
the complicated the relationship between
cause and effect is relatively easy to
figure out and doesn't change any
meaningful fashion so we can build
expertise and then we can we can set
goals and we can develop strategies to
be able to achieve those goals and that
toolkit is effectively the complicated
toolkit and in in the context of
complexity this entire toolkit doesn't
work cause and effect or not obviously
easily related things are changing too
rapidly you can't actually have goals
and strategies in complexity what what
you do have is you have principles and
so what I'd like to do today is is talk
about a particular principle to take
that as the object of inquiry and the
principle I want to focus on is I think
quite useful in the contemporary
environment and that is the principle of
closing loops okay so to walk through
that principle what I want to start with
this is the body the human body is our
example and what we can say is that the
human body can be perceived as a mesh of
a wide variety of distinct cells and
organelles and organs and metabolic
processes and other biological processes
that hang together in a homeostatic
equilibrium which is to say that this
this complex massive of billions and
billions of different cells is somehow
able to work together to achieve the
ability to actually maintain conditions
in its environment that are conducive to
the long-term well-being of the system
itself and a big part of that is the the
way that this system connects together
in closed loops and so what I mean is
for example let's take a given process
like so the contraction of the muscle
fiber
that process requires certain inputs so
it plugs into the environment and looks
to the environment to provide the inputs
that it needs to be able to achieve its
particular function it then provides
that function whatever it happens to be
and as one of the consequences of that
it produces outputs and now here's the
key those outputs and are the waste
products of the process and it is
necessary to achieve homeostatic
equilibrium that there be some other
process that plugs in to those outputs
and has the capacity could convert that
waste to convert those outputs into
useful inputs to provide other useful
functions so this is a closed loop and
the point is that the human body as it
evolved biologic system is actually
extraordinarily effective at closing
loops if you imagine for example the the
notion that you can eat just an apple
and that would provide enough nutrition
in the form of calories and energy and
other kinds of nutrients to power this
whole giant body for hours even you know
running around lifting things and
thinking about stuff that this is an
extraordinary amount of efficiency and
then a relatively minor amount of
ultimate waste product achieve this
level of efficiency and maintain
homeostatic oh Librium these leap
closures require a couple of different
characteristics one of course is the
fact that you actually have to close the
loop in the sense that for every output
there needs to be some other process
that receives it as an input but then to
there actually is to be a symmetry
between the capacity of output and the
capacity of input all right so if my my
motion of producing lactic acid at a
rate that is much faster than my body's
ability to process that lactic acid then
what happens is that I will run into
what you might think of as pure pure
waste and this pure waste will show up
as toxic in the body so then I need to
have some kind of mechanism whereby
either the rate of production or the
rate of processing is is is brought back
into symmetry and so maybe something
happens where my muscles just can't fire
any law
there's just too much lactic acid in the
environment so I can't produce any more
elastic acid and then the body can
ultimately get itself back into
equilibrium and if I can't do that if
the rate of production continues to
outstrip the writ of processing then I
end up with a toxic environment and of
course certain levels this will begin to
break down the well functioning of the
broader system and then of course
eventually would lead to death and so so
that's that we have a homeostatic
equilibrium driven by a mesh of
different systems and processes that are
able to at a very high level of
effectiveness close all loops now of
course there's a limit to this this
effectiveness that there is always going
to be some portion of output that can't
actually be turned back into input and
so this of course is pure waste and the
body has to have a mechanism for
grabbing that pure waste isolating it
pulling out of the environment where
it's currently toxic putting it into
other environments like the colon in the
bladder and then exiting it from the
body all together and that's that and
that's that's it like that's how one of
the primary mechanisms whereby we're
able to maintain equilibrium but now
things of course get more interesting
because I can I can say that I'm exiting
pure waste from my body into the outside
but properly of course what I'm really
doing is I'm and exiting things from one
inside into a nested larger inside
because of course my body is part of a
larger eco systems part of the
environment so when the bear shits in
the woods the output from the bear
becomes input to dung beetles and fungi
and other microbes that are then taking
that as inputs that are processing it
into outputs that are useful in the
broader context of the ecosystem and we
know that actually that the
effectiveness of these loop closures in
long-standing ecosystems are also
remarkably effective and in some sense
this is kind of the point of biology of
life is that life exists on the basis of
its capacity to maximally effectively
process energy that comes into the
system resources that come into the
system with the absolute
waist and then outputs that waist is as
delicately and efficiently as possible
to maintain the minimum amount of
toxicity and you know over the past
couple of billion years the biological
environment has gotten pretty good at
that now of course there are limits
we are always bounded by thermodynamics
and so are our pale blue dot is by
necessity connected as an open system to
the Sun which provides us with most of
our free energy and to the the legacy
energy embodied in various material
resources in on the earth but within
those contexts would be the biological
environment does a remarkably effective
job at closing loops so then we bring
human beings back into the into the
story because one of the things that we
have been able to accomplish is the
ability to extract and concentrate
resources at a level that is just orders
and orders of magnitude more intense
then Nature has ever proceeded and had
to deal with in the past so as a
consequence the rate of production of
output of human industrial social
processes is just way a symmetric to the
natural environments capacity to take
these as inputs and convert them back
into closed loops so as a consequence of
course for producing waste all over the
place that we're producing waste
nitrogen and waste phosphorus we're
producing waste carbon dioxide we're
producing waste uranium were producing
waste estrogen I mean just the out the
output of our human environment is open
loops all over the place and this
consequence waste all over the place and
as a consequence of the sort of
increasing rate of output with no real
significant increase in the rate of
input toxicity everywhere and so
obviously as just as in the case of the
human body the consequence of this
toxicity is a breakdown of the well
functioning of the processing system the
homeostatic system and then ultimately
death which may occur within in the
lifetime of the people watching this
video so it's
worth contemplating but but now things
actually get even more interesting
because when we're dealing with humans
we've so far been talking about this
question in this problem of closed loops
in the context of the physical of
molecules and physical nature but we we
can and should also talk about it in the
context of the social when our our
social environment Civic Society is
itself something of an ecosystem we have
relationships we have communication
channels we have dispositions and these
are affected by the flows across those
channels and they when they're working
well they also operate as some kind of
homeostatic system that is able to
maintain its the well-being of the whole
over some enduring period of time so
take for example something like
advertising and in this context we can
we can think of advertising as something
which has a very very open loop within
the ecosystem of civic society that the
the outputs of advertising are the sorts
of things that so quite significantly
outstrip the capacity of our collective
sense making mechanisms ability to
process them into useful goods then it
produces just an enormous amount of
toxicity
you know advertising has the breaks down
the the efficiency of our communications
channels and it breaks down the quality
of our relationships and generates a
lack of trust occur in generates ambient
distrust and it creates an enormous
amount of noise much the same way to say
lactic acid in a muscle system and our
collective intelligence does not yet
have any meaningful capability to
process this noise and these breakdowns
of relationships at a level vaguely
symmetric to the accelerating capacity
to produce it now of course for some
period of time we're able to more or
less get along but in the context of
exponential technology social media
Infotech et cetera
ecology neuroscience and the rate of the
output of this waste into the social
environment now so vastly outstrips the
capacity of the environment to endure it
much less to process it that we're
beginning to see a breakdown of civil
society so on the one hand we need to
close those loose we need to find some
way of building in those symmetries of
output and input we need to build in
mechanisms that rate control output at
input so as to maintaining within some
sort of equilibrium or so as to avoid
some level of catastrophic collapse
death at the level of civil society but
if we close the loop and go back to the
first point at the physical level the
problem is actually even more
significant because not only do we need
to avoid a meaningful degradation of our
collective intelligence we actually need
to witness a quite substantial increase
in capacity because obviously if we want
to go about being able to have the level
of perception and the level of
understanding and the level of
skillfulness in collective action to be
able to be equal to the amount of output
that we generate in turn our natural
environment if we want to be able to
monitor the presence of nitrogen in
every cubic centimeter of the ocean and
then be able to understand how that
nitrogen fits into various kinds of
processes both negative and positive and
then be able to generate mechanisms
whereby we can either process it or
reduce the input so that it actually
maintains homeostatic equilibrium with
the entire global ecosystem well that's
a lot more than we can do right now so
we actually need to quite substantially
upgrade our collective capacity to
engage in these kinds of activities if
we want to have any chance of being able
to be equal to the problem of closing
loops at the physical level and I think
that needs to be taken seriously I my
sense is that there's a strong intuitive
sense that there is a need to close
loop's at the physical level I think
there's also a strong intuitive sense of
the need to close loops at the social
level and frankly now even at the
personal relational level but it's a far
cry from sensing that something is
necessary to being able to actually take
responsibility for it to being able to
really quite deliberately operate in a
truly agenting capacity in relationship
to a problem of this magnitude it means
being able to actually go slowly and
understand how much you can actually do
and then understand how you can go about
building the capacity building the
individual and collective sovereignty
that is adequate to the level of
complexity the problem domain under
investigation of course that's a lot and
we'll have to the subject of another
conversation
I hope this was helpful